What if just one
lifestyle change
could help you
avoid getting cancer,
or diabetes,
or heart disease,
or high blood pressure?
This one change could cut
your risk of chronic disease
and add years to your life.
Well, the simple solution to
so many of these problems
is to eat a healthy diet.
In other words, one centered
around whole plant foods.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I'm your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
What if you
only ate foods
that took into account
your specific metabolism –
your family history,
how much you exercise.
Would that be helpful?
Today we start with the question,
how useful is personalized nutrition?
Personalized nutrition is rooted in the
concept that one size does not fit all,
and who doesn't want
to think they're special?
The concept of personalized nutrition
is inherently appealing to the human ego.
Simple messages recognizing
individuality therefore resonate
deeply with consumers,
explaining the popularity of such
messages in sales and marketing,
even to the point of
manufacturing personalized food
for people's uniqueness,
suggesting 3D Food Printing
as a good candidate
for food customization.
Now, there certainly are some
legitimate differences between people.
Some have a peanut allergy and
keel over if they eat a peanut.
And others have celiac disease
and have to avoid gluten,
or genetically are lactose intolerant.
There's an enzyme mutation
common in some parts of Asia
that protects against alcoholism
because people with it can't
metabolize alcohol as efficiently,
so toxic metabolites build up.
I did a fascinating video about fast
versus slow caffeine metabolizers
and the difference in health benefits.
That actually extends
to athletic performance.
Caffeine is ergogenic,
performance enhancing,
but only in fast metabolizers,
shaving more than a minute
off 10 kilometers of cycling,
whereas slower
metabolizers got no benefit,
or caffeine actually
slows them down,
adding two minutes to their cycling
time, depending on which kind of genes
they have that codes the
enzyme that breaks it down.
But for most people, in most situations,
we are more similar than different.
While there's undoubtedly a specific
minority of individuals who clearly
require a more personalized
approach to nutrition, there is presently
insufficient rationale for truly personalized
nutrition for the majority of people.
Yet there is an astonishing number
of direct-to-consumer genetic testing
companies that have proliferated,
offering personalized nutrition advice,
for example, supplement-hawking
companies claiming to help consumers
optimize micronutrient status on the
basis of a handful of genetic variants.
But the majority of these variants
explain just a few percent
of the difference in levels
between individuals.
Personalized nutrition is part
of a broader push towards
"personalized medicine," also
known as "precision medicine"
given the "massive cultural allure"
of personal control over prevention,
diagnosis, and treatment of disease,
stimulating demand and prompting
intense commercialization.
But unlike monogenetic diseases,
which are rare genetic diseases
caused by a single malfunctioning gene
like hemophilia or sickle cell anemia,
most diseases are caused by a complex
interaction between multiple genes
with environmental factors, which pose
a major challenge for the realization
of personalized medicine.
Take something like
adult stature, for example.
We've found at least 40 locations
on our chromosomes that have been
associated with human height,
which is strongly inherited.
The genes from your parents account
for about 80% of the difference
in height between people, yet all
those dozens of genes we've found
explain only about 5% of
height variation between people.
Researchers find those genetic links
by using what are called genome-wide
association studies, where you
scan through all the chromosomes
and look for statistical
associations between diseases
and any particular stretches of DNA.
Okay, that's interesting,
but what companies marketing
genetic susceptibility tests are doing
is reinterpreting these data as if
they were predictive of individual risks.
But all you're really getting are
modest genetic associations
with a slight increase in the risk of
disease and with little predictive value
when compared to more
significant contributions of things
we already know
like lifestyle behaviors.
Currently, the practice of utilizing
the DNA of an individual to predict
disease has been judged to provide
little or no useful information.
For example, let's say your genetic
analysis says you're at slightly greater
risk for some grave condition compared
to others in your ancestral group.
This person was given advice
to exercise, keep their weight down,
not drink too much alcohol, and eat
fruits, vegetables, and whole grains.
Okay, solid advice,
but this is how we should live
regardless of our genetic risk.
And we all know, or should know,
these simple, bedrock strategies
to reduce the risk of common
chronic diseases in general.
The problem, of course, is that
very few individuals live that way.
Actually, to be more precise,
almost nobody lives that way.
That's not just hyperbole.
Nationwide surveys show that
nearly the entire U.S. population
consumes a diet that is not on par
with even the wimpy dietary
guidelines recommendations.
In other words, almost no one in the
United States is eating a healthy diet.
Studies like that remind us that from
the perspective of public health,
worrying about personalizing
our preventive strategies
based on genetic risk information
borders on the absurd.
In our next story
we ask ourselves,
if doctors can eliminate
some of our leading killers
by treating the underlying
causes of chronic disease,
why don’t more doctors do it?
Though I was trained as
a general practitioner,
my chosen specialty is
lifestyle medicine.
Yes, most of the reasons people
go to see their doctors
is for diseases that could
have been prevented,
but "Lifestyle medicine is not just
about preventing chronic disease(s)"
"but also about
treating (them)."
And not just treating
the disease,
it's treating the
causes of disease.
If people just did
4 simple things—
not smoking, exercising
a half hour a day,
eating a diet that emphasizes
whole plant foods,
and not becoming
obese,
that may prevent most
cases of diabetes,
and heart attacks, half of strokes,
and a third of cancers.
Even modest changes may
be more effective
in reducing cardiovascular disease,
high blood pressure,
heart failure, stroke,
cancer, diabetes,
and all-cause mortality than almost
any other medical intervention.
The key differences between
conventional medicine
and lifestyle medicine is instead
of just treating risk factors
we treat the underlying
causes of disease,
as described in this
landmark editorial.
See "Typically doctors treat
'risk factors' for disease"
"such as giving a lifetime's
worth of medications"
"to lower high blood pressure,
elevated blood sugar, and high cholesterol."
But think about it.
High blood pressure is just a symptom
of diseased dysfunctional arteries.
Yes, you can artificially lower
blood pressure with drugs,
but that's not treating
the underlying cause,
which often comes down to things
like diet and exercise,
"the penicillin of
lifestyle medicine".
"Disregarding the
underlying (cause)"
"and treating only risk
factors is somewhat like"
"mopping up the floor around
an over-flowing sink"
"instead of (just) turning
off the faucet,"
"which is why medications usually have
to be taken for a lifetime."
"If a floor is flooded as a
result of a dripping tap,"
"it is of little use to mop up (around)
the floor unless the tap is turned off."
"The water from the tap represents
the cause of disease,"
"the flooded floor the diseases
filling (up) our hospital beds."
Yet, "medical students
learn far more about"
"methods of floor mopping than
about turning off taps"
"and doctors who are specialists
in mops and brushes"
"can earn infinitely
more money than"
"those dedicated to
shutting off taps."
And the drug companies
are more than happy
to sells rolls
of paper towels,
so patients can buy
a new roll every day
for the rest
of their lives.
Paraphrasing Ogden Nash, modern medicine
is making great progress,
but just headed in
the wrong direction.
Preventive medicine, is, frankly,
bad for business….
When the underlying lifestyle
causes are addressed,
patients often are able to stop
taking medication or avoid surgery.
We spend billions cracking
people's chests open,
but only rarely does it actually
prolong anyone's life.
In contrast, how about wiping out
at least 90% of heart disease?
Think about it…
"Heart disease accounts
for more premature death"
00:03:10,8 --> 00:03:13,66
"than any other illness and is
almost completely preventable"
"simply by changing
diet and lifestyle."
And those same changes
can prevent or reverse
many other chronic diseases as well—
the same dietary changes.
So why don't more
doctors do it?
Well, one reason is doctors
don't get paid to do it.
"No one profits from
lifestyle medicine,"
"so it is not part of medical
education or practice."
Presently, physicians lack training
and financial incentives,
"So they continue to do
what they know how to do:"
"prescribe medication
and perform surgery."
After Dean Ornish proved
you could reverse
our #1 cause of death,
heart disease,
open up arteries without drugs,
without surgery,
just with a plant-based diet and
other healthy lifestyle changes,
he thought that his
studies would have
a "meaningful effect on the practice
of mainstream cardiology."
After all, a cure for
our #1 killler?!
But, he admits,
he was mistaken.
Physician reimbursement,
he realized,
"is a much more powerful determinant
of medical practice than research."
Reimbursement more
than research.
Salary over science.
Wealth versus health.
Not a very flattering portrayal
of the healing profession,
but hey, if docs won't do
it without getting paid,
let's get them paid.
So, Dr. Ornish went
to Washington
arguing that, "Look, if we train
and pay for doctors"
"to learn how to help
patients address"
"the real causes of disease
with lifestyle medicine"
"and not just treat
disease risk factors"
"we could save trillions!"
And that's just talking heart disease,
diabetes, prostate, and breast cancer.
The Take Back Your Health Act was
introduced in the U.S. Senate
"to induce doctors to learn and
practice lifestyle medicine"
not only because it works BETTER,
but here's the critical factor:
physicians will
be paid to do it.
The bill died...
just like the millions of
Americans will continue to do
with reversible
chronic diseases.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
My latest two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”,
available on e-book, audiobook,
or actual book.
And the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”,
with more than 100 recipes for
delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of my books go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.